[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Seven]
[第七集]
The topic of today's meeting is
今天开会的议题是
reforming Peking University's teaching work.
改革北大的教学工作
This subject,
这个话题呀
five years prior, when I was Minister of Education,
五年前是我当教育总长的时候
is what I brought up.
提出来的
Today, we can truly put it into practice.
今天呢 才能真正地去践行
This shows the difficulty of reform.
由此可见 改革之艰难哪
In the face of such difficult reforms,
面对这么艰难的改革
there must be a condition:
必须要有一个条件哪
that is unity.
那就是团结
The first step of reform
改革的第一步
is to set up a board of trustees.
是要成立学校的评议会
This board of trustees
这个评议会
is composed of the president and deans of various discplines
由校长和各科的学长
as well as professors represented by trustees.
还有教授评议员组成
For every five professors in the school,
在全校每五个教授中间
one trustee must be elected.
去选出一名评议员
The president is the chief trustee,
校长是评议长
and all major school matters
凡是学校的重大事情
must be examined and approved by the board of trustees,
都得经过评议会 审核通过
such as the development of various rules and regulations,
如制定各种规章条例
determining the abolition and establishment of disciplines
决定学科废与立
or of academic titles of professors,
教师的学衔
the school budget, and so on.
还有学校的经费 预算等等
All have to go through the university board of trustees.
都得要经过校评议委员会
Therefore, we obligate every professor of each discipline
因此 我们要把各科的教授
to be reappointed.
重新聘任
To bring the best talents,
要把优秀的人才
including foreign.
包括国外的
We must all accept into Peking University
我们都要吸纳到北大来
and abolish those unqualified professors,
要裁撤那些不合格的教授
including foreign professors.
包括外籍教授
This task is very complicated.
这个工作很复杂
So we should start with liberal arts.
所以我们要从文科先做起
May Mr. Zhongfu put all his energy into this area
请仲甫先生把精力都放在这一块
and come up with a detailed plan as soon as possible.
尽快拿出具体的方案
Hand it over to the school board of trustees for discussion and approval.
交给校委会讨论通过
Understood.
是
Good.
好
That's all for today's meeting.
今天这个会议就先开到这儿
Professor Gu.
辜教授
This is over, too.
这也散会了
The two of us can spar in the school grounds on campus.
咱们俩可以校园小操场切磋切磋
The others can attend.
其他人可以列席
Please.
请啊
Brother Zhongfu, please stay.
仲甫兄 您请留步
I want to talk to you.
我有话跟你说
Let's sit down and talk.
来我们坐下聊一下
Brother Zhongfu is a researcher of Chinese history.
仲甫兄是研究中国历史的
[Cai Yuanpei, styled Jiemin, President of Peking University]
[蔡元培 字 孑民 北京大学校长]
Do you know
你可知当下
which era of Chinese history
它使我想起了
it reminds me of at the moment?
中国历史上的哪一个时代
Hot.
烫
The Spring and Autumn period and Warring States period before Qin dynasty.
先秦的春秋战国时代
What was the situation of the era at that time?
当时那个时代是个什么状况呢
The Western Zhou dynasty destroyed rites and music.
西周灭 礼乐崩
At the time, no one knew where to go from there.
当时啊 没人知道往下该如何走
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, Dean of Liberal Arts at Peking University]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 北京大学文科学长]
Everyone was looking for a way out.
大家都在寻找出路
But the key point
可是关键点在于
is that in that period,
是那个时期啊
there was no unified royal authority,
没有一个统一的王权限制
so all kinds of learning came out.
于是各种各样的学问就出来了
You say yours, I'll say mine.
你说你的 我说我的
So it's a pleasure to fight it out.
于是争得就不亦乐乎
Right.
是啊
The Hundred Schools of Thought. How lively.
百家争鸣 好不热闹
Therefore, culture is the forerunner of politics.
所以 文化是政治的先导
Brother Zhongfu, I don't know if you've noticed
仲甫兄 我不知道你发现没有
the period we are in now is very similar to that of the pre-Qin.
我们现在很像先秦的那个时代
No matter what era the future develops into,
无论将来发展到什么时代
it will eventually be guided by our
它终将是以我们
present advocacy of new culture.
今天所倡导的新文化为先导的
It is also based on the break with the old culture.
也是与旧文化的决裂为基础的
No.
不
I disagree with you.
我不同意你的观点
Culture is not separable.
这个文化啊 它是割不断的
New culture can only
它新文化只能在
grow in the swaddling clothes of the old culture.
旧文化的襁褓中生长
And as for old culture, it's only sublation and innovation.
对旧文化 它只是扬弃和革新
Academic research cannot be uniform.
在学术研究上不能搞清一色
We must encourage and support a Hundred Schools of Thought.
要鼓励和支持百家争鸣
What Mister means is
先生的意思是
Peking University should continue to hire
北大要继续聘任
these old-fashioned die-hard professors.
这些复古派 顽固派的教授
Yes.
是的
But the new culture
可是新文化
is grass that just broke through the soil.
是一个刚破土的小草啊
How can you stand
怎么经得起
the crazy trampling of the old forces?
这旧势力的疯狂践踏呀
What's wrong?
怎么了
Are you, Chen Duxiu, not confident?
你陈独秀都不自信了
What did you tell me yesterday?
你昨天是怎么跟我说的
I mean, I want to fight
我是说我渴望战斗
but I really don't want to
可是我真的不愿意
associate with these stubborn old-fashioned professors
跟这些思想顽固的复古派
all day long.
终日为伍
Look at this Gu Hongming.
你看这辜鸿铭
The moment I arrived, I was given a show of strength.
一来就给我来个下马威
Of course I'm going to spar with him on the school grounds.
我当然要跟他约战小操场了
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄啊
As the Dean of Liberal Arts at Peking University,
作为北大的文科学长
you can't be unable to tolerate people.
不能容不得人哪
You know, people and culture are the most complicated.
你知道 人和文化最复杂
In today's chaotic era,
在当今这么一个混沌时代
in fact, everyone is looking for a way out for the country,
其实每个人都在为国家寻找出路
but the thinking is different.
只是思路不同黑了
You take for example Gu Hongming.
你比如说辜鸿铭
Although some people say that he is a die-hard royalist,
尽管有人说他是铁杆的保皇派
he is also full of justice akin to the Spring and Autumn period,
满嘴的春秋大义
but we have to admit
但是我们不得不承认
Gu Hongming's exposition and criticism of Western culture
辜鸿铭对西洋文化的揭露和批判
is still of great positive significance.
还是很有积极意义的
People like you and I who have been abroad for many years
像你我这种在外国待了多年的人
should feel the same way.
应该是感同身受
Right?
是不是
Master Cai's words, is of great benefit to me.
蔡公一席话 受益匪浅
You are flattering me.
过奖了
In addition to you and I,
还有 就是你我
This Mr. Liu Shipei, a fellow of the Yuewang Association, (democratic revolutionary group founded in 1905 by Chen Duxiu and Bo Wenwei)
这个岳王会的同人刘师培先生
he recently sent me a letter.
他最近给我来了封信
This person...
这个人哪
He is one of the famous Six Chuan Gentlemen (pro-Yuan monarchist organisation)
他是著名的筹安六君子
and also wrote to Yuan Shikai
而且还给袁世凯写过
"On Restoring the Ancient Ways to the Country under the Monarch".
《君政复古论》
What did he say in his letter sent to me?
他给我来信怎么说呢
First, it refutes
一是驳斤了
Hu Shi's "On Literary Improvement".
胡适的《文学改良刍议》
Second,
二是
he actively asked to teach at Peking University.
他积极地要求到北大来任教
This Liu Shipei
这个刘师培呀
has done a lot of foolish things.
做了很多 事
But he is a scholar.
不过他是一个读书人
Everything he did was for the sake of his livelihood.
权作稻粱而已
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄啊
My dream
我的理想
is for Peking University to become
北大 它要成为
a great academic stage with outstanding talents,
群贤毕至的学术大舞台
because only in this way
因为只有这样
can we breed a healthy new culture.
才能滋生出健康的新文化
I asked Brother Zhongfu to come to Peking University as the Dean of Liberal Arts.
我请仲甫兄到北大来任文科学长
That is the origin of all.
盖源于此
Brother Jiemin.
孑民兄
Now I miss it very much.
现在我非常怀念
The times we were making bombs together,
我们在一起做炸弹那时候
at least that time,
至少那时候
you didn't talk in circles.
你说话不绕来绕去的
I see.
我懂了
You mean not only to keep Gu Hongming
你的意思不仅要把辜鸿铭留下来
and let me fight with him,
让我跟他接着战斗
but also to bring the old-fashioned Liu Shipei
还要把复古派的老顽固刘师培
to Peking University, right?
也要请进北大来 对吗
I carefully understand Master Cai's ingenuity.
蔡公匠心 我悉心领会
I have a lot to live up to.
不负重托
Thank you, Mr. Zhongfu.
谢谢仲甫先生
Students, the fate of the literary revolution
同学们 文学革命之气运
has not been brewing for a day.
酝酿已非一日
[Gu Hongming, styled Tangsheng, Professor at Peking University]
[辜鸿铭 字 汤生 北京大学教授]
The first to raise the banner of righteousness
其首举义旗之急先锋
was my friend Hu Shi,
则为吾友胡适
willing to brave the enemies of the national scholars,
余甘冒全国学究之敌
to raise the banner of the cultural revolutionary army
高张文化革命军大旗
Consider my friend's solidarity.
以为吾友之声援
The banner is written with
旗上大书特书
the three great doctrines of our revolutionary army.
吾革命军三大主义
I say, overthrow the ornate, aristocratic literature,
曰 推倒雕琢的阿读的贵族文学
build a simple, lyrical, national literature.
建设平易的抒情的国民文学
I say, overthrow the stale, extravagant, classical literature,
曰 推倒陈腐的铺张的古典文学
build a fresh, honest, realistic literature.
建设新鲜的立诚的写实文学
I say, overthrow the intricate, obscure, pastoral literature,
曰 推倒迁晦的艰涩的山林文学
build a clear, popular, social literature.
建设明了的通俗的社会文学
Aye! Aye! Aye!
好 好 好
Aye!
好
Mr. Chen has said it well!
陈先生说得好
Aye! Aye! Aye!
好 好 好
Aye!
好
Don't move. Don't move.
别动 别动
Everyone's in class.
上课了都
Almost there. Almost there. Almost there.
快好 快好了 快好了
How long can you go for?
你能挺多久
Mister is coming!
先生来了
Mister is coming! Mister is coming!
先生来了 先生来了
Enough. Enough. Enough.
行行行
Rise.
起
Bow.
礼
Greetings, sir.
先生好
[Huang Kan, styled Jigang, Professor at Peking University]
[黄侃 字 李刚 北京大学教授]
Greetings, students. Sit.
同学们好 坐
Fellow students,
各位同学
today let's all enjoy this strange piece of writing.
咱们今天哪奇文共赏之
Recently in America,
近日在美国
there was an unmatured youngster named Hu Shi
有一个叫胡适的黄毛小子
who wrote several poems in vernacular Chinese.
用白话写了几首诗
Unexpectedly, it was published in the famous
居然在鼎鼎大名的
"New Youth" magazine
《新青年》 杂志上刊登了
and unexpectedly even won some applause.
居然还获得了一片叫好
It's ridiculous!
真可笑之极
I've read this article.
我见此文
It's like seeing a bunch of cattle manure.
真是如见济济牛类
Causes one to be unable to swallow
令人食不下咽
and think like a barn fly.
思之如茅棚虻蝇
Making people thin and sleepless.
惹人瘦不安眠
Therefore, from now on,
故 从即日起
I will make a rule.
我便要立一个规矩
That is, before class every day,
那便是 每日上课之前
I will spend twenty minutes
我要用二十分钟的时间
criticizing this writing in vernacular, free verse in vernacular,
痛批这白话文 白话诗
bit by bit until it falls over, rotten and stinking.
直到把它批倒批臭为止
Mr. Jigang.
季刚先生
If you don't want the "New Youth"
您扔在地上那本
that you threw on the ground.
《新青年》 不要了吧
Can I pick it up?
那我捡起来行吗
You can consider it a bargain.
您就当便宜我了
Wait, wait.
等等
Put it back.
把它放回来
Didn't you not want it?
不是不要了吗
Pick it up.
捡哪
Mister can disagree with the ideas in the book,
先生可以不同意书上说的观念
but don't throw the book away.
但是不至于扔书啊
What ideas?
什么观念
It's all nonsense!
说的都是狗屁
I'm going to throw it a hundred times, a thousand times!
我还要再扔它一百次一千次
Pick it up.
捡哪
Sir, let me pick it up for you.
先生 我来帮您捡
Sir.
先生
However many times you throw it
以后您扔多少次
is however many times I will help you to pick it up.
我就帮您捡多少次
I've taken on the task.
这活儿 我包圆了
Go back!
回去吧
Of course.
得嘞
Sir!
先生
If you throw it again, I'll also pick it up for you.
您要是再扔 我也帮您捡
Students! Pick it up or not?
同学们 捡不捡
Pick it up!
捡
Quiet!
安静
Sit down.
坐下
Students, let's get back on topic.
同学们 咱们言归正传
Writing poems in vernacular Chinese.
用白话写诗
What a joke.
笑话
This is just lunatic ravings!
那就是痴人说梦
Self-delusions!
是自痴行径
What is poetry?
诗是什么
The essentials of poetry. What is the essence of poetry?
诗的要义 诗的精髓又是什么
To sum it up in one word,
用一字而概之
it is refinement.
那就是雅
What is vernacular?
白话又是什么
It can also be summed up in one word,
也可以一字而蔽之
it is vulgar.
那就是俗
One is refined, one is vulgar.
一个雅 一个俗
One is holy, one is grotesque.
一个在天上 一个在地上
Can we mentioned these in the same breath?
岂可同日而语啊
Can we pass off fish eyes as pearls?
岂可鱼目混珠
Sir.
先生
I think literature should be both refined and popular.
我以为文学应该是雅俗共赏
Old-style poetry and vernacular poetry go hand in hand.
旧体诗和白话诗并行不悖
Wouldn't free development be better?
自由发展 岂不是更好
Confusion!
糊涂啊
Poetry is poetry, prose is prose, and speech is speech.
这诗是诗文是文话是话
If you want to represent everything in vernacular,
要用白话代表一切
why do you need poetry?
那还要诗文做什么
What is the point of Peking University?
还要北大做什么
Do you still need to travel thousands of miles
你还用得着千里招招地
from Hunan to Beijing to go to school?
从湖南来到北京上学吗
Sir.
先生
Vernacular poetry is really popular now.
现在白话诗真的特别受欢迎
Female students in normal universities
女高师的学生
keep Mr. Shizhi's poems in their hands every day,
每天都适之先生的诗不离手
[Deng Zhongxia, styled Zhonghao, Student at Peking University]
[邓中夏 字 仲澥 北京大学学生]
and they organize vernacular poetry readings.
而且她们组织了白话诗朗诵会呢
Exactly.
就是
Right.
对啊
Our Peking University student union
我们北大学生会啊
is also preparing for a poetry recital.
也正在筹备诗歌朗诵会
Many professors have come to attend.
很多教授都来参加呢
such as Professor Chen Duxiu,
比如陈独秀教授
Professor Qian Xuantong,
钱玄同教授
and Professor Shen Yinmo.
还有沈尹默教授
They all come to attend.
都来参加呢
Right!
对呀
They all want to come!
这要去呀
Yeah! Yeah!
是呀 是呀
Quiet!
安静
Deng Zhongxia, I ask you.
邓中夏 我来问你
Whose student are you?
你到底是谁的学生
Are you my, Huang Kan's, protege?
是我黄侃的门生啊
Or that Chen Duxiu's filial son and grandson?
还是那陈独秀的孝子贤孙
Sir.
先生
I love my teacher,
吾爱吾师
I love the truth more.
吾更爱真理
Well, since you're talking about the truth.
好 既然你说到真理
Then I'll tell you what truth is.
那我就告诉你什么是真理
What the teacher says is truth.
老师讲的就是真理
Dignity is truth.
师道尊严就是真理
You are arguing irrationally.
您那是强词夺理
Guo Xingang, what did you say there?
郭心刚 你跟那儿嘟囊什么
He said you argue irrationally!
他说您强词夺理
Quiet!
安静
Guo Xingang, Deng Zhongxia.
郭心刚 邓中夏
You two ignore discipline.
你二人无视纪律
Gathering people to make trouble and scold the teacher.
聚众闹事 唇骂老师
Outrageous!
岂有此理
Both of you, get lost.
你二人给我消失
Get lost!
消失
Get lost! Get lost! Get lost!
消失 消失 消失
Quiet!
安静
A wall of dirty soil cannot be plastered over.
粪土之墙 不可圬也
Let's go, let's get lost.
走吧 消失
Good. Students, let's continue our class.
好 同学们 咱们继续上课
Today's lecture is on "The Literary Mind and the Carving of Dragons".
今天讲《文心雕龙》
Open your textbooks.
打开课本
Gentlemen, students,
先生们 同学们
let's begin our meeting.
下面咱们开会
Liberal arts professor Huang Kan has submitted a complaint in writing to Mr. Cai
文科教授黄保致信蔡先生
regarding the students Deng Zhongxia and Guo Xingang
诉学生邓中夏 郭心刚
for disrupting classroom order,
扰乱课堂秩序
insulting the teacher, and deviating from Confucian doctrine,
唇骂师长 背经离道
and requests the appropriate disciplinary actions be taken.
要求给予校纪处分
Mister Cai has instructed the school to lead an investigation
蔡先生责成学校牵头检查
and ascertain the facts of the matter,
弄清原委
as well as propose suggestions on how to handle it.
并提出处理意见
For the sake of prudence,
为了慎重起见
Mr. Cai is personally attending this meeting.
蔡先生也亲自参加了此次讨论会
Professor Huang Kan is invited to begin the litigations.
下面有请黄保教授诉讼
Mr. Wu just now misspoke.
刚才许先生是口误啊
This can't be called a lawsuit.
不能说是诉讼
We are here to have a discussion today,
我们今天是个讨论会
to express our own opinions.
应该是发表自己的意见
Mr. Huang Kan is invited to express his opinion.
请黄侃先生发表自己的意见
Peking University has always respected the dignity of the teaching profession.
我们北大历来是师道尊严
It is a law-abiding school with rules.
有规矩 讲规矩的学校
But recently,
可是近来
the so-called New Culture school of thought has enticed
在所谓新文化思潮的蛊惑之下
a section of students to be confused in their thinking and lacking in their discipline.
部分学生思想混乱 纪律懈怠
To the point of openly stirring up trouble in class,
竟公然在课堂之上起哄
and insulting their teachers.
唇骂老师
It is truly preposterous.
真岂有此理
If this can be tolerated, what cannot?
是可忍熟不可忍
The culprits Guo Xingang and Deng Zhongxia
主犯孰心刚 邓中夏
must be disciplined by the school as a warning to others.
必须受到校纪处分 以儆效尤
What?
这
Guo Xingang and Deng Zhongxia...
这邓中夏郭心刚
Hurling abuse at teachers?
唇骂教授
Really!
真是
What about the dignity of the teaching profession?
师道尊严还要不要啊
Quiet down, everyone.
大家静一静
Everyone, quiet. Everyone, quiet down.
大家静一静静一静
The student Deng Zhongxia is invited to address the litigations against him.
请邓中夏同学辩诉
No, not litigations.
不
To present his side of the argument.
辩论
You may speak.
你发言吧
Honoured teachers, gentlemen.
各位师长 各位先生
We didn't disrupt classroom conduct.
我们并没有扰乱课堂纪律
We merely didn't entirely agree
我们只不过是不太同意
with Professor Huang Kan's viewpoint on vernacular Chinese verse,
黄侃教授对于白话诗的观点
and his attitude in the classroom
以及他在课堂上
towards "New Youth" magazine.
对于 《新青年》 杂志的行为
In the classroom we entered into some discussion
我们在课堂上进行了一些交流
and debate.
和辩论
I believe
我以为
this should be under the purview of academic freedom.
这应该属于学术自由的范畴
And not "hurling abuse at the teacher."
而不属于什么辱骂老师
Deng Zhongxia,
邓中夏
how can you lie?
你怎么能撒荒呢
Why don't you tell the truth?
你为什么不说实话
I testify that Guo Xingang
我证明 郭心刚同学
truly did insult Professor Huang Kan, using specious arguments and sophistry.
确实辱骂黄侃教授是强词夺理
We all saw it.
大家都看到了
Yes!
对对
We saw it all.
全看到了
Gentlemen,
诸位先生
Professor Huang Kan personally attacked
黄侃教授在课堂上以一己之见
"New Youth" and vernacular poetry in class.
攻击 《新青年》 和白话诗
He said "New Youth" was fly-covered cow dung
说《新青年》 是牛粪苍蝇
and that the writers of vernacular Chinese were idiots.
说白话诗的作者是白痴
But also that his words were the truth,
而且说他的话才是真理
unquestionably so.
且不容置疑
Is this not preposterous sophistry?
这难道不就是强词夺理吗
It is! It is!
就是啊 就是啊
Quiet, everyone.
大家静一静
Quiet, everyone. Quiet.
大家静一静 静一静
Dean Chen, this is an affair of the liberal arts department.
陈学长 这是你们文科的事情
Please state your thoughts.
请你发表意见
The origin of this has to do with vernacular writing
这件事情的缘起 是白话文
and "New Youth" magazine.
和《新青年》杂志
I am heavily implicated in this matter
我是重要的当事人
and am in fact the biggest idiot, according to Professor Wang Kan.
就是黄侃教授所说的最大的白痴
Vernacular speech belongs to those who are idiots
白话就是大傻子
so as an idiot I better remain silent
那我这个傻子就保持沉默
and not speak any idiocies.
不说傻话了啊
Gentlemen,
各位
it is very clear to me what the whole story is.
我看事情的原委已经很清楚了
Who is right and who is wrong is already self evident.
谁是谁非已然不辩自明
In my opinion, the party subjected to disciplinary action
我以为 该受到处分的
should not be a few students who dare to presevere with the truth
不是几个敢于坚持真理的同学
but rather the one who used the classroom to publicly vent their personal spite.
而是利用课堂泄私愤 骂大街
The thief who cries thief, Professor Huang Kan.
又恶人先告状的黄侃教授
Huang Kan was vulgar in his speech,
黄侃言语粗俗
absurd in his conduct
行为荒诞
and falls far short of Peking University's motto
与北大的校训
and Master Cai's objectives for our school.
和蔡公的办学宗旨大相径庭
Behaviour simply not deserving of being called a teacher.
简直愧为人师
This kind of person should be cleared out of Peking University.
这样的人 就该清除出北大
Right!
对
Does everyone agree?
大家说是不是
I agree!
我同意
Cleared out of Peking University!
清除出北大
We shouldn't want this kind of professor!
我们不应该要这样的教授
Exactly!
就是
Stop your hubbub.
不要喧哗
You shut up!
尔等闭嘴
Mr. Qian Xuantong, you were too harsh.
钱玄同先生 言重了吧
Huang Jigang acted in the interest of the public good,
黄季刚出于公心
to uphold our national culture and refute heresies.
维护国粹 驳斥异端
It is not a crime.
何罪之有
Completely unreasonable remarks!
完全是奇谈怪论
[Shen Yinmo, Professor at Peking University]
北京大学教授沈尹默
In that case, is it a crime
那同学们拥护新文化
for students to support new culture,
仗义执言
to take a stand on a matter of principle?
又何罪之有呢
Invalid!
谬论
Valid!
正论
Evil heresies!
异端邪说
It is right and proper to support new culture.
拥护新文化 天经地义
Everyone, please sit down. Please sit down.
大家都坐下 都坐下
Let's hear what Mr. Cai has to say.
听蔡先生讲几句
Today, attending this...
今天参加这个
this discussion forum,
这个讨论会啊
I had not planned to speak.
我是没有准备要说话的
But I am moved by everyone's
不过刚才大家讨论得非常激烈
fierce and frank participation just now,
坦率地说 也感染了我
so I will say a few words.
那我就说一些
To speak bluntly,
我直言不讳地说
I think this discussion forum is very good.
我认为这个讨论会很好
To discuss problems freely when they arise, and collect suggestions.
出了问题自由讨论 集思广益
This, in itself,
这本身是
is an aspect of our reform measures at Peking University.
我们北大改革的一项举措
What everyone was just discussing
大家刚才讨论的
is a question of the school's rules and regulations.
是有关学校的校规问题
We do have customs at Peking University.
我们北大是有规矩的
In my opinion, Peking University's most important custom
我以为北大最大的规矩
is scientific democracy, inclusive, in all its forms.
那就是科学民主 兼容并包
What is the premise of scientific democracy?
科学民主的前提是什么
It is equality.
是平等
Everyone is equal before the truth.
真理面前人人平等
Not to mention teachers and students.
更何况师生呢
Inclusive, in all its forms.
兼容并包
That refers to everyone
就是大家
being able to express their academic opinions.
都能发表自己的学术观点
To hold forth to their heart's content.
畅所欲言嘛
This should be our school tradition at Peking University.
这应该是我们北大的学风
I believe discussions like today's
我相信像今天这样的讨论
will occur often at Peking University in the future.
以后在北大会经常发生
I also hope this kind of discussion forum,
我也希望像这样的讨论会
even if it is a bit fierce,
哪怕是再激烈一点
as long as it is useful for teaching,
只要对教学有益
the more there are, the merrier.
多多益善哪
Well said!
好好好
[Spring, 1917]
[1917年春]
Slow down, don't fall.
慢点 别摔着
Don't let the two of them trip.
别把它俩踩着了
These days, once things are looking up, time just flies by.
这个日子一有了盼头就过得飞快
Three months have passed in the blink of an eye.
三个月一脱眼就过了
I thought these three months were quite long.
这三个月我倒觉得挺久的
People are always rushing to argue with me.
老是有人赶着跟我吵架
Trembling with fear, walking on thin ice.
战战兢兢 如履薄冰
Oh, please.
得了吧
It takes two to tango.
一个巴掌拍不响
My wife knows me.
知我者夫人也
Wife, take it easy.
夫人 别忙了
So busy with this and that as soon as you get here.
一来了就干这干那的
Can't you take a little break?
就不能歇息一下吗
If I take a break,
我歇息了
when will this house get tidied?
这家什么时候能收拾出来呀
Wife,
夫人
come, rest a while.
来 过来歇息一下
Drink some tea.
喝杯茶
Set aside your job. I can do it too.
你那活放那儿我也能干
You do it?
你干
You only know how to flap your lips.
你就会动嘴
Why don't you just save me some trouble.
少给我添乱行不行你
The more you help, the more fuss.
你帮忙 越帮越忙
I feel winter in Beijing
我觉得呀 北京这冬天
is more comfortable than in Shanghai.
就是比上海舒服
With a fire, it's warmer inside than outside.
屋里生了火比外边暖和
In Shanghai, during winter,
上海的冬天
it's even colder inside than outside.
屋子里比外边还冷
Yannian got several patches of frostbite on his feet.
延年的脚上都冻出好几处冻疮了
How come?
为什么
From setting up those stall outside.
还不是出去摆地摊冻的
Has medicine been applied?
抹药了吗
It's been applied.
抹了
But he won't listen to my advice.
但是他不听我劝
Still insists on setting up the stalls.
非得出去继续摆啊
Let me tell you something interesting.
跟你说个有意思的事吧
Did you know, after you left,
知道吗 你走了以后
Yannian suddenly came to visit one day.
延年有一天突然上门
To apologize to me.
来跟我道
Said that I was so concerned about them before,
说是以前我那么惦记他们
helped them so much,
那么帮助他们
that he never expressed any gratitude towards me,
他都从来没有对我表示过感谢
and that it was inappropriate of him.
实在太不应该了
And then he told me to stop worrying.
还跟我说让我放心
He can take care of himself now.
现在他可以照应好自己
No more false bravado like before.
以后不会像以前那么逞强了
No more false bravado.
不会那么逞强
Setting up stalls even with frostbitten feet.
那脚上都出冻疮了还摆摊
That's not false bravado?
还不逞强
That's enough.
行了
He's a child after all.
他毕竟是个孩子
It's already pretty good that he's this thoughtful.
能这么想就已经很不错了
He told me a great deal that day.
那天 他跟我聊了很多
I feel,
我觉得
he's truly grown-up a lot more compared to before.
他现在确实比以前懂事了
But, right now he really enamoured with Wu Zhihui,
但是 他现在很崇拜吴稚晖
fascinated by his anarchism.
迷上了他的无政府主义
He's determined to do a work-study program in France.
一心想去法国勤工俭学
Along with Qiaonian, he's even living at school now.
现在带着养年都住校了
But they're still editors at "New Youth"
不过他们还在《新青年》当编务
helping with publishing.
搞发行
Wang Mengzou signed a contract with the two of them.
汪孟邹也给他俩签了合同
Each according to their work.
按劳付酬
So they've figured out both school and life for themselves.
所以他俩的学习和生活都解决了
You don't need to worry.
你就放心吧
It's not that easy to go to France for work-study.
去法国勤工俭学哪儿那么容易
France is fighting a war.
法国正在打仗
Don't know when it's going to end.
什么时候结束还不知道呢
The two of them can't stay
他们两个不能总待在
in that French evening class forever.
那个法文补习班吧
Before, I wanted them to learn self-discipline.
以前我是为了磨炼他们
Now it seems like
现在看来
it would be more suitable for them to come to Beijing.
他们还是到北京比较适合
I heard Wu Zhihui say
我听吴稚晖说呀
that he is planning,
他现在正和蔡元培
with Cai Yuanpei and Li Shizeng,
还有李石曾策划
to establish a Sino-French university in France.
在法国要办一所中法大学
If that is successful,
要是这事弄成了
then those two kids would have a way out.
那两个孩子不就有着落了吗
Can't just follow whatever Wu Zhihui says.
不能什么事都听那个吴稚晖的
That guy looks rough, but he's actually quite shrewd.
那个人看似粗糙 实则有心计
Kind face, cruel heart.
面善心狠
Hard to figure him out.
让人捉摸不定
Yannian shouldn't get too close to him.
延年不能跟他走得太近
It's no good.
不行
I have to write him a letter. Advise him.
我得给他写封信 嘱咐嘱咐他
You're writing a letter?
你写啊
You write.
你写
I dictate. You write.
我说 你写
And go to the pharmacy.
另外 去药铺
Buy him a few boxes of tiger balm.
再给他买几盒虎镖鲨油冻裂膏
Send it together.
一块给他寄过去
That's better.
这还差不多
Brother Zhongfu!
仲甫兄
At the ceramic glaze factory
我们在琉璃厂
we found this old thing for sister-in-law.
给嫂子淘换了个老玩意儿
Careful, careful.
小心小心
This must be sister-in-law. [Li Dazhao, styled Shou Chang, editor of Tiger Daily]
这位是嫂子吧
Let me make some introductions.
来 介绍一下
Li Dazhao,
李大钊
gifted scholar from Waseda University
日本早稻田大学的才子
Now, with Mr. Zhang Shizhao,
现如今跟章士钊先生
editors of "Tiger"
一起编《甲寅》
and also co-editor
也是我们《新青年》的
of our "New Youth."
同人编辑
Hello.
你好
Zhao Shiyan,
赵世炎
student at Beijing Normal University's affiliated middle school, [styled Qin Sheng]
北京高师附中的学生
disciple of Shou Chang,
守常的弟子
and an alumnus from your school.
也算是你的校友
Mrs. Chen.
师母好
Hello, Shiyan.
你好 世炎
Guo Xingang, Bai Lan.
郭心刚 白兰
I met them in Japan.
都是我在日本认识的小友
Hello, Mrs. Chen.
师母好
Hello.
你们好
Sister-in-law, take a look at this. Do you like it?
嫂子 您看看这个喜不喜欢
It's too wonderful. Such a wonderful thing.
太好了 这么好的东西
Where should it be placed?
给您放在哪儿
Thanks.
谢谢
How about in the bedroom?
那要不放那个卧室
Great.
好
That room, there.
就那个房间
Shiyan,
世炎
help move it in.
帮忙放进去
Sure.
好
Thank you.
谢谢啊
It's so nice.
真是好东西
Thought you'd have need for it.
想必您用得着
Shou Chang, it's an honour to meet you at last.
守常 我对你可是久仰了
You article "New Youth," is deeply moving.
你写的《青春》荡气回肠
I often read it aloud when I'm by myself.
我经常一个人独自吟诵呢
I really liked it.
真是喜欢
Sister-in-law, you are too generous with your praise.
嫂子 您谬奖了
I've actually read your poetry before.
其实您的诗我读过
Graceful and subdued like Li Qingzhao, heartbreaking. [southen Song dynasty female poet]
婉约如李清照 让人心碎
What poetry?
哪是什么诗啊
That was just made up nonsense and venting.
就是些胡诌和发泄罢了
Let's first have a seat.
我们先坐下吧
After sitting down, you two can continue to flatter each other.
坐下以后你们再互相吹捧
How's that?
好不好
Really!
真是的
Zhimei, Henian,
子美 鹤年
come and see Mr. Dazhao.
来 见过大钊先生 来
Hello, Mr. Dazhao.
大钊先生好
Hello, you two darlings.
两个小宝贝好
They look like you.
像你啊
Take this, play over there.
拿着东西 到那边去玩啊
You two sit.
你们先坐
Alright.
好
Here, Shou Chang, sit.
来 守常 坐
Sister-in-law,
嫂子
now that you're here, I'm finally liberated.
您来了之后我算是解放了啊
What do you mean by that?
此话怎讲啊
This guy of yours,
您家这位
mooching off of me every day after he got to Beijing.
到了北京以后天天蹭我的饭
It's one thing to mooch,
你说蹭就蹭吧
but he even disdained my cooking, saying it's inferior to yours.
还东嫌弃我手艺没有您好
Left me both mentally and physically exhausted.
搞得我是心力交痒呀
What I've been eating these last three months has been pitiful.
这三个月的饭我也吃得很崩溃
You see!
你看
I understand.
我听明白了
From now on Mr. Shou Chang,
从现在开始 守常先生
you must come to eat at our home often.
您得经常来我们家吃饭
You have to mooch back all the food he mooched from you!
您得把他蹭的饭给蹭回去
What are we eating today?
今儿吃什么
Shou Chang,
守常
you've been in Beijing for about a year now.
你这到北京也一年多了
You should move your family here.
该把家眷接过来了
That's right.
是啊
Mr. Shou Chang is so valiant.
守常先生一身英气
You must make a great couple.
肯定和夫人郎才女貌
A marriage of mutual respect.
举案齐眉了
Sister-in-law, you didn't know this.
嫂夫人您是不知道
My wife and I were an arranged child marriage.
其实我跟夫人呢是娃娃亲
When I was ten, my family was short of womenfolk.
我十岁那年 家里头缺少女眷
So I was married off.
就让我成亲了
My wife is six years older than me,
夫人大我六岁
and can't read very many characters. She's a genuine village girl.
大字不识几个 是个地道的村姑
But we are very fond of each other,
但是我俩感情很好
and have had four children together.
前后生了四个孩子
Two of them died young.
就是夭折了两个
Mr. Shou Chang is of noble character and very admirable.
守常先生品德高贵 令人钦佩
No matter what, you need to settle down your family.
无论怎样 都要把家安顿好
Why don't you, sooner rather than later,
你还是尽早把夫人和孩子
move your wife and children to Beijing.
接到北京来吧
I've actually had this thought.
其实我倒是有这个想法
But the situation in Beijing right now is unstable.
但是现在北京局势不稳
Incessant fighting between warlords.
军阀混战
Let's wait and see.
过过再说吧
Peking University is appointing professors again.
北大现在正在重新聘任教授
Why don't you and Gao Yihan come to Peking University.
你和高一涵一起到北大来吧
Peking University?
北大
I've seen the list of appointees
你们文科这次报过来的
for your Liberal Arts department.
聘任教授名单我看了
Not bad. Very comprehensively thought out.
不错 考虑得很周全
But there's a problem.
但是有一个问题
The education ministry wouldn't process
一下子报这么多
so many at once.
它教育部不会批
I think we should do it in batches, to get around it.
我想啊 我们还是分批次
Separate them in different groups.
分不同途径给解决
For example, Liu Shipei,
比如 像刘师培
Zhang Shizhao,
章士钊
could be put on file with the education ministry.
可以在教育部备案嘛
Hello, Sirs.
先生好
Hello, students.
同学好
And as for the younger people,
至于年轻人
particularly the ones who aren't well-known,
特别是那些名不见经传
or those without academic qualifications,
又没有学历的人
we'll use the pathway
我们分途径
or sorting them in batches.
分批次给他解决
At present, there are three categories of young talents.
现在青年才俊主要分为三类
Those in the US usually have proper academic credentials.
在美国的一般都有正规的学位
Those in Japan rarely have official diplomas.
在日本的就很少有正式的文凭了
And then there are those who didn't attend university,
还有一些没上过大学
but have some degree of renown in China.
但是在国内也小有名气
Like Liu Bannong, Liang Shuming etc.
像刘半农啊 梁漱溟等
"From wind and rain comes China's vital force,"
九州生气恃风雷
"What a great pity not to hear a neighing horse!"
万马齐喑究可哀
"I urge the Lord of Heaven to shake us up again,"
我劝天公重抖擞
"And grant us talent not bound to a single kind."
不拘一格降人材
The last few lines of Gong Zichen's poem
龚自珍这首诗的后两句
will serve as Peking University's general principle for appointing professors.
作为我们北大聘任教授的总原则
What "not bound to a single kind" means is--
所谓不拘一格那就是要
Greetings, sir.
先生好
Greetings, student.
同学好
is learning to be flexible and accomodate different arrangements and ways.
就要学会变通各种方式和途径
For example, Zhang Shizhao, Li Dazhao
你比如说章士钊 李大钊
They are in the middle of running "Jiayin", unable to leave it. (?)
他们正在办《甲寅》 离不开
Especially Zhang Shizhao, who told me
尤其是章士钊他跟我怎么说
He will only be the head of Peking University's library for half a year.
他只做北大图书馆的主任就半年
"After half a year, I'll get Li Dazhao to take over."
半年之后 我让李大钊去接替
This way Li Dazhao's problem is solved.
这样大钊的问题就解决了
Another example, Liu Banong, he has no educational background.
再比如刘半农他没有学历啊
So we will appoint him to be the professor of preparatory courses.
那我们就聘任他作为预科教授
In short, attract talent by any means necessary.
总而言之 千方百计地招揽人才
So we can have talented people all gathered in Peking University.
让人才都拢到北大来
Right.
是啊
Right now, there are some talents in other parts of the country.
现在有一些人才呢在外地
Even abroad.
甚至是国外
They won't be able to get here for some time.
一时还不能到位
I am wondering if we should also take them into consideration.
我在想 是不是也要先考虑他们
First get them in.
先进来
People like Hu Shi, Wu Yu.
像胡适啊 吴虞这样的
Of course.
那当然
Hushi is a talent that is hard to come by.
胡适是不可多得的人才呀
Since he has --
他既然有
Greetings, sir.
先生好
Greetings, student.
同学好
Since he has this PhD,
他既然有这个博士学位
appointing him,
聘任他
making an exception will not cause any problems.
破格也不会有什么问题呀
Just now you talked about overseas.
你刚才说到外地
Greetings, sir.
先生好
Greetings, student.
同学好
There is one called Yang Changji, do you know?
有一个叫杨昌济你认识吗
He is teaching in Changsha, Hunan.
他在湖南长沙教书
A literature bachelor's degree from the University of Aberdeen.
爱丁堡大学的文学学士
Greetings, sir.
先生好
Greetings, student.
同学好
How about it. Let's hire him at Peking University.
怎么样 我们把他聘用到北大来
Sure!
好啊
[Hunan province, first established teacher-training school]
[湖南省立第一师范学校]
Mr. Yi
易先生
Greetings, sir.
先生好
How's it going here with you?
你这儿 都忙得怎么样了
You can see it is already almost tidied up here. [Yi Baisha, styled Yue Cun, new culture movement scholar]
您看这已经收拾得差不多了
Come, I'll do some introductions.
来我给你们介绍一下啊
This is Yi Baisha, Mr. Yi.
他是易白沙易先生
He is one of the chief writers of "New Youth"
是咱们《新青年》 的主笔之一
and the author of "A Critique of Confucius"
也是 《孔子评议》 的作者
Sir, hello. [Mao Zedong, styled Runzhi, student of Hunan province's first normal university]
先生 您好
Hello.
你好
This person is our student.
这位啊 是咱们的学生
Called Mao Zedong.
叫毛泽东
He is our "New Youth's"
他可是 咱们《新青年》
zealous follower.
铁杆的追随者啊
As a matter of fact,
这不
hearing that you came,
听说您来了呀
he wouldn't stop bothering me
就缠着我
to take him to see you
让我带他 到您这儿来
and ask for guidance on some problems.
向您请教一些问题
As soon as he starts talking about politics
他呀 谈及国事
he always brings up "New Youth."
言中必有《新青年》
He even nitpicks for us.
他还给咱们《新青年》
Finding errors and correcting mistakes in "New Youth."
找碴儿 纠错
Is that right?
是吗
In that case I want to hear about
那我倒要听听
what errors you've found.
你都纠出什么错来了
Sir. I believe Mr. Chen Duxiu's
我认为 陈独秀先生
six guiding principles in New Youth
对新青年的六项标准啊
is not very comprehensive.
不太全面
I believe at the very least, there needs to be an additional
我认为 至少要加上
"Be sturdy, and not frail."
健壮的 而非体弱的
Those foreigners
那些外国人
don't they always say we are the sick men of Asia?
不是经常说我们是东亚病夫吗
Sick men, they are not able to save China.
病夫 是救不了中国的
Good, very well said.
好 说得好
When there's a chance, I will surely take your idea
有机会我一定把你的意见
and convey it to Mr. Zhongfu.
转达给仲甫先生
Sir, thank you.
先生 谢谢您
How's this,
这样
why don't you two have a chat.
你们哪 就先聊
I still have matters to be busy with.
我还有事要忙
I'll... take my leave first.
就 先告辞了
Take care, sir.
先生慢走
Sir.
先生
I have a presumptuous request.
我有一个不情之请
I... have written an essay,
我呢 写了一篇文章
and would like to ask you for some pointers.
想请您给我 指点一下
Sure.
好
Please, sit.
你请坐
"A Study of Physical Education"
《体育之研究》
Our nation is wanting in strenght. The military spirit has not been encouraged;
国力苶弱 武风不振
The physical condition of the population deteriorates daily.
民族之体质 日趋轻细
This is an extremely disturbing phenomenon.
此甚可忧之现象也
The promoters of physical education have no grasped the essence of the problem,
提倡之者 不得其本
and therefore, their efforts, though prolonged, have not been effective.
久而无效 长是不改
Our weakness wil increase further...
弱且加甚
Impressive!
不俗啊
The start of the essay is impressive!
开篇不俗啊
I invite you, sir, to lend your advice.
还请先生 多多指点
Good essay , good essay.
好文章 好文章
It really is a good essay!
真是好文章
This is the first essay I've seen
这还是我看过
that systematically investigates physical education in China.
第一篇 系统研究中国体育的文章
This, with regards to promoting New Youth, New Culture
这对于推动新青年 新文化
and our promotion of new life
还有我们推动的新生活
is of great benefit.
是有很好的效益的
Honestly speaking,
老实说
I wouldn't be able to write an essay like this.
我都写不出这样的文章来
Sir, you flatter me.
先生 您过奖了
How's this?
这样
I'll write a recommendation letter for you.
我给你写一封推荐信
Have this essay
你把这篇文章
sent to Mr. Chen Duxiu in Beijing.
寄给北京的陈独秀先生
I believe
我相信
he will surely publish it.
他一定会刊用的
Sir.
先生
If you feel that this piece of essay is written well.
如果您觉得这篇文章写得不错
I will send it to Mr. Chen Duxiu right away.
我就马上寄给陈独秀先生
As for
至于
the recommendation letter.
推荐信
It is not needed.
就不用了
I'm afraid it will influence Mr. Chen Duxiu's judgement.
我怕影响陈先生的判断
Alright.
好
You have a bright future.
有出息
Scissors sharpening! Knife sharpening! [Jiangan Lane, Beijing]
[北京箭杆胡同] 磨剪子嘞 戗菜刀
This essay,
这篇文章呢
Liu Bannong looked at it and thought it was well written.
刘半农看过之后觉得写得不错
Very insightful.
很有见解
However, given that there are no comparable articles
但是呢鉴于尚没有
about physical education to use as a reference,
关于体育研究之类的文章做参照
plus the fact
再加上
the author is still a student of a teacher-training school,
作者还是一个师范学校的学生
its impact will be limited.
缺乏影响力
We can first put it aside, and talk about it again later. (?)
可以先放一放 以后再说
Then, what's your opinion?
那你的意见呢
What I mean is that the article itself is not bad,
我的意思呢是文章本身不错
but
但是呢
all the articles published in this issues are from well-known authors.
这个咱们这期发的都是名家
We can put it aside for the time being.
可以先放一放
I don't agree with this opinion from you two.
我不同意你俩的意见
I feel this essay
我觉得这篇文章
can be the start of research into physical education.
可以说是体育研究的开篇之作
It's significant for providing guidance for youth.
对青年是有指导意义的
This author with the penname "Twenty-Eight Strokes"
这个笔名二十八画生的作者
is Mao Zedong
叫毛泽东
Only twenty four years old.
才二十四岁
To be able to write an essay like this is very amazing.
能写出这样的文章很了不起
This publication of articles like this
这种文章的发表
is important for motivating and encouraging youth.
那对青年是有激励和促进的意义
My opinion is to publish it in this issue.
我的意见这一期就发
Okay, I'll go back and discuss it with Bannong.
好我回去跟半农商量一下
What's there to discuss? Publish it right away.
还商量什么 直接发
Everyone,
各位
Today is our Peking University's
今天是我们北京大学
first discussion forum.
第一届评议会议
The subject is to look into and discuss
议题是研究讨论
Peking University's list of appointed professors in the Liberal Arts department.
北京大学文科教授聘任的名单
Right now, Mr. Chen Duxiu is invited
现在 请陈独秀学长
to provide an explanation of the list of names for us.
来给我们就名单做说明
Dear committee members,
各位评议员
the list of names that has been given to everyone
现在提供给各位的这份名单
is based on what Mr. Cai has set
是根据蔡先生确定的
as Peking University's general educational reform guidelines.
北大教学改革总体思路
It is based on a systemic investigation of
在对文科各个门类
the top talents in each area of the humanities
顶尖人才的系统摸底的基础上
as well as consideration of what is pratically required
再针对我们北大文科
to construct our Liberal Arts department at Peking University.
建设的实际需求拟定的
It follows Mr. Cai's thoughts
按照蔡先生
on establishing Peking University's long term development,
立足北大长远发展的指导思想
and applies his principle of not being bound to only one way of selecting talent.
和不拘一格降人材的用人原则
Our list of names pays particular attention
我们这个名单对中青年人才
to young and middle-aged people with talent.
给予了较多的关注
To sum it up,
总的来说
this list of names consists of three types of talents.
这份名单大致包括三种人才
The first is experts with achievements and influence
一是在学界公认的
who are academically well-known.
有成绩有影响的专家
Such as Zhang Shizhao,
如章士钊
Gu Hongming, Yang Changji
辜鸿铭 杨昌济
Liu Shipei, Huang Kan, and so on.
刘师培 黄侃等
The second is those who are abroad and finished studying
是国外留学学成
or about to return to China,
或即将归国的
who have already shown some promise.
已经崭露头 角的青年才俊
Such as Jiang Menglin, Hu Shi, Xu Beihong
如蒋梦麟 胡适 徐悲鸿
Gao Yihan, Li Dazhao, and so on.
高一涵 李大钊等
The third is those with no educational background
是没有学历
but truly has genuine talent,
但确实有真才实学
with some small amount of renown.
且已小有名气的英才
Such as Liang Shuming, Liu Bannong, and so on.
如梁漱溟 刘半农等
What needs to be emphasized is
特别需要说明的是
This is a big list, divided into batches, ranks
我们这是一份分批 分等次
different positions, and appointment tracks.
分不同聘任途径的大名单
It is a list of qualified people,
实际上是一份资格名单
and not necessarily a list of names we will immediately hire.
并不是我们马上就要聘用的名单
Seeing as there is quite a number of people,
鉴于人数较多
and committee members are already very familiar
且各位评议员对所列人员
with some names on the list,
都已经很熟悉了
I won't introduce them one by one.
那我就不再一一介绍了
Now, each committee members is invited to do their duty
现在请各评议员履行职责
and start the discussion.
开始评议吧
In my opinion, the standard for professors at Peking Univesity
我以为 北大教授的标准
should combine both ability and integrity, putting virtue first.
应是德才兼备 以德为先
Some people, although they are educated and famous,
有些人虽然有学问 有名气
were willing running dogs of Yuan Shikai,
但是却甘愿做袁世凯的走狗
and notorious royalists.
是臭名昭著的保皇党
People like this,
这样的人
in my view, have no right to be professors at the new Peking University.
我认为没有资格做新北大的教授
Brother Deqian,
德潜贤弟
you have your heart set on smashing my rice bowl. [taking away my job]
你这是想成心砸我的饭碗啊
Was I not telling the truth?
难道我说的不是事实吗
Gentlemen Qian,
钱爷
Of those named on the list, or sitting here,
在座的和名单里
I am not the only royalist.
保皇党可不止我一个人哪
Say it clearly! Who is a running dog!
说清楚啊 谁是走狗啊
Say it clearly!
说清楚
Who is a royalist?
谁是保皇党
Do you still need me to say it?
这还用我说吗
It is self evident.
不辩自明呀
Apologies, Mr. Qian,
对不起 钱先生
forgive me for interrupting your speech.
恕我冒犯 打断你的发言
What you said is right.
你说得对
Peking University's appointed professors need to have both ability and integrity.
北大聘任教授要德才兼备
I totally agree.
我完全同意
But if you say that royalists are without virtue by definition,
但是 你说保皇党即是无德
then I beg to differ.
这我不敢苟同
At present, as China is undergoing turbulent transformation,
当今中国变局转型
we are all seeking a way out.
大家都在寻找出路
All kinds of political views should be in conflict with each other.
各种政见理应相互激荡
The Peking University I envision is for teaching and educating people,
我北京大学是教书育人
a place of research and learning.
研究学问的地方
For there to be all kinds of debates and academic point of views,
各种学术观点争论呢
is a normal phenomenon.
它是个正常现象
It is said that people of noble character can be in disagreement but get along with one another.
正可谓君子和而不同嘛
All the more reason for us to be inclusive.
更应该兼容并包啊
For example, in the study of culture,
比如说 文化研究
should we modernize or remain traditional?
维新还是守旧
All can give their own view, let a hundred schools of thought contend!
都可以各抒己见 百家争鸣嘛
Only in this way, with this progressive culture,
唯此 这个先进的文化
could we distinguish ourselves.
才能脱颖而出啊
Mr. Chen,
陈学长
you are the flag carrier of new culture.
您是新文化的旗手
What do you think, amongst those present today,
您说说看 今天在座的当中
who, because they venerate Confucius,
有哪一个因为是尊孔
are without virtue?
他就是无德呢
I've never thought those who venerate Confucius are without virtue.
我从来不认为尊孔即是无德
There are two kinds of people who venerate Confucius.
尊孔分为两种
Those who are academic Confucians.
一种是学问尊孔
And those who are political Confucians.
一种是政治尊孔
The discipline of Confucianism
这个孔子儒学
was originally one school of thought out of the hundred
原本是春秋诸子百家中的
from the Spring and Autumn Period.
一个流派
One field of knowledge.
一种学问
It is wide-ranging and profound, long-standing and well-established.
博大精深 源远流长